<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods visitation in a sermon preached at Leicester, at an ordinary visitation. By T.P.</title>
            <author>Pestell, Thomas, 1584?-1659?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09506</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19788</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107478</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843177</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843177</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7890</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09506)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7890)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1579:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods visitation in a sermon preached at Leicester, at an ordinary visitation. By T.P.</title>
                  <author>Pestell, Thomas, 1584?-1659?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston for Robert Allott, and are to be sold at his shop in Saint Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Beare,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Thomas Pestell.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7890:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7890:1"/>
            <p>GODS VISITATION: IN A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT LEICESTER, AT AN ORDINARY VISITATION. By T. P.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAIAH 10.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>What will you doe in the day of Viſitation and of Deſolation?</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngston</hi> for <hi>Robert Allott,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, at the ſigne of the <hi>Beare.</hi> 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7890:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7890:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, AND HIS WORTHY FRINDS, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. RO. COATS, MAIOR: M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. THO. <hi>Chapman,</hi> Recorder: M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iames Ellis,</hi> Alderman: M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. T.G. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. W.S. with all the Societie of <hi>that ancient Incorporation of</hi> Leiceſter, <hi>Grace and Peace, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot denie but in my youth, among other weakeneſſes, I yeelded to the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of printing Sermons, at requeſt of ſuch as had a power over me. But ſince I grew both an elder man, and a poore retired Vicar in an obſcure angle of the Countrey, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolu'd againſt any more ſuch aduentures. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold your vehement entreaties (M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Ellis</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>G.</hi>) and charging me with my reſpecting Gods Glory, haue drawen theſe poore Meditations abroad: yet with this proteſtation, that I deſire (if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) no eye might be taken of from richer ſtuffe and worthier Bookes (wherewith the world a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds) to looke on this, ſaue only yours, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I haue euer yet found ſo much, &amp; ſo vndeſerued fauour, that peraduenture euen for that affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate fauors ſake, this will ſeeme to you better then in deed it is. being only plaine matter and not ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate in ſtile or ornaments of quotations. With it (if that be any amends) I dedicate my ſelfe and my beſt endeuours to reſt at your Seruice. And ſo praying for the continuance of all Gods bleſſings vpon you all. I remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord Ieſu, <hi>THOMAS PESTELL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:7890:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am importuned to importune you, to doe that which I hope your wiſedome will wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly conſent vnto: yet as I doe heartily wiſh it, ſo I must earnestly intreat you, or elſe I ſhall betray the trust that I am put in. The matter is, that you would be pleaſed both for a generall and a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular good; to cauſe your late both excellent, and learned Sermon, preached at the Viſitation at Leicester, to be put in print, that the vertue thereof, by the power of God, may diſperſe it ſelfe to them that heard it not. I deſire it not onely for your owne ſake, though no doubt it would make your name to ſmell like a pretious oyntment in the Church of God, but for the glorie of Gods ſake, which would be much increaſed by the publike view thereof. And you are bound in conſcience, to doe the beſt ſeruice you can, in ſetting forth your Masters glory with all alacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that hath made you ſo able a Minister to performe it. Therefore let me intreat you, not to deny the ſetting forth of that, which may giue many thouſands of Gods people much cauſe to bleſſe God for it, and you alſo praying to God for his aſsistance, in this and all your godly endeuors, I commend you and all yours, to his protection, that is able to keepe you and all yours for euer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to be commanded, IAMES ELLIS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7890:3"/>
            <head>GODS VISITATION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IOB, 31.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>What then ſhall I doe when he riſeth vp. And when God ſhall viſit. What ſhall I anſwere him?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Text comprehends thoſe two noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which comprehend all. <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi> For the whole world was in <hi>God</hi> before hee made it, and wheir hee made it, he made it all for <hi>Man:</hi> and made it all ouer againe in <hi>Man.</hi> And made <hi>Man</hi> in his owne Image like <hi>God,</hi> and that Image, defac'd and <hi>Man</hi> loſt to recouer him, and make him new he vouchſaf'd to make himſelfe <hi>Man. God</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> in one perſon: and the conſummation of all his workes, (which is alſo the conſuinmation of all <hi>Mans</hi> hopes) is to bring <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> into one place. But this muſt await his time and obey his owne methode, which hee ſo frames by his powerfull hands, his vnderſtanding and his will, that as in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mercie, ſo with his Honour and his Iuſtice too, hee may aſſume them to that place of Glory. Hee will giue grace and glory, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. but grace
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7890:4"/>firſt, therefore enlightning rectifying, purifying their vnderſtanding, will, affections, hewing and poliſhing, pruning and dreſſing, euery ſtone in the building, euery branch in the vine: and in that nature we finde him here, viſiting, looking to the wayes of <hi>Man,</hi> that <hi>Man</hi> might looke vp to him.</p>
            <p>Briefely (not to reflect yet on the coherence, at which I ſhall touch anon in place conuenient enough.) The text deliuers vs two parts. Firſt, <hi>Gods</hi> office. Secondly, <hi>Mans</hi> office. His to viſit, <hi>Mans</hi> to debate and anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>God</hi> is the viſitour. The Schoole makes theſe degrees of perceiuing <hi>God</hi> in names. Firſt, <hi>negati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, remotionis.</hi> What <hi>God</hi> is not, not the Sunne, Moone, not finite, mutable. Secondly, <hi>perfectionis, affirmationis,</hi> when what is moſt excellent in things create we apply to him by way of analogie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, ſo wee call him iuſt, mercifull, high, glorious. Thirdly, of ſupereminence, ſuch as this of a Viſitour, gathered from his action here, and ioyn'd with the Emphaſis of my text — when he ſhall viſite. Men are viſitours, but they more eaſily anſwered, their place and power but deriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues from this primitiue. He, he the grand viſier, <hi>Altiſsimus</hi> — moſt high. So that to <hi>Gods</hi> abſolute power, euery where preſence, this attribute and this tranſcendent ability of an holy watcher a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peruiſor is proper. 'Tis proper blazon, and title ſutable, denoting throughout theſe words, not height alone; and power, and ſuperioritie, — when he ſhall ſtand vp: but maieſtie and terrour too — what ſhall I anſwere him?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:7890:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
We haue found his office, but will <hi>God</hi> performe it. 'Tis a queſtion of mens performing their offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and a queſtion too of falſe <hi>Gods.</hi> They had an Idoll in Egypt call'd by ſuch a name <hi>Baal Zephon. Dominus ſpeculae;</hi> Lord of the watch-tower, to fright their fugitiues; but when <hi>Moſes</hi> and the people of Iſrael paſt that way, and pitched the campe there, this god was aſleepe, but he that kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth Iſrael neither ſlumbers nor ſleepes. He kept his Iſrael then and ſince, hee made good the title then, and ſince, and dare we queſtion it now? But how doth <hi>God</hi> viſite? Search the ſcriptures, they teſtifie of him; Thoſe bookes are morall, to teach <hi>Man</hi> his office, the whole duty of <hi>Man,</hi> to make the <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>God</hi> perfect to euery good worke, but they are hiſtoricall too, and propheticall too; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing vs what <hi>God</hi> hath done, and what <hi>God</hi> will doe. Looke then to thoſe records and wee ſhall finde what and when, and how, in his ſeuerall Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitations. His Viſitations are his actions, Action is from intrinſique vertue, vertue there is none ſuch in <hi>God</hi> as ſuppoſes infirmitie, or imperfection, as faith, hope, &amp;c. But ſuch as argue perfection, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, iuſtice, wiſedome, bounty, power. According with theſe, wee finde his Viſits: firſt in generall, then with reference to men, both wayes, their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in mercy, ſinne vpon their perſons in iuſtice.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In generall, in all places, and ouer all things aboue. Heauen is his Throne where he ouerlooks the orders and royall armies of his Angels, aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, deſcending, in the materiall Heauen, diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that numberleſſe varietie of thoſe glorious
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7890:5"/>Starres, calling them all by their names in the ayry Heauen amidſt thoſe flockes of fowle, his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence extending to the fall of euery little ſparrow. If we goe downe to the Sea, amongſt thoſe infinite ſhoales and innumerable fiſhes, there wee ſee his wonders in the deepe; or if we goe deeper. If we deſcend to Hell, be is there alſo, binding the fury of infernall ſpirits: and for the earth, it is his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole, vnmou'd he ſits in midſt of Heauen, and yet they be the eyes of the Lord that runne to and fro through the whole earth. <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.10. raigning aboue, yet containing and vpholding all below, compaſſing all about, yet piercing all within. But applyed to <hi>Men,</hi> they are the eyes of <hi>God</hi> which behold, and his eye-liddes which trie the children of men. But firſt the perſons in mercy, as wee vſe the word in our Viſitation of friends, or of the ſicke. And of this kinde (as well pleaſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with) is that where <hi>God</hi> doubles it; <hi>Viſitans, viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui. Exod.</hi> 3.16. — Viſites and remembers, viſites and reſtores, <hi>Ier.</hi> 17. <hi>vlt.</hi> This is called the face, the beauty of his holineſſe when hee cauſes the light of his countenance to ariſe. Then ſecondly ſinnes vpon the perſons, and this changeth the aſpect — he frownes and bends the browes, ſets his face a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; viſiting the iniquitie of the fathers vpon the children vnto the third and fourth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.18. firſt, or laſt: on them, or theirs, by no meanes clearing the guilty. Then he is deſcribed to viſite in thunder and earthquake, in ſtorme and tempeſt. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.6. and in this ſenſe the word is vſed among the Prophets promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7890:5"/>for recompenſing, puniſhing, auenging, and euen this threatned on his owne people, tender as the apple of his eye, and his chiefe treaſure; aboue all nations. <hi>Oſe.</hi> 1.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.2. <hi>Ier.</hi> 11. <hi>Eſa</hi> 10.3.</p>
            <p>Wee may not omit his mercifull Viſitation, ſhould it not ſhew like a piece of ingratitude not to touch here firſt, though our voyage bee to that of finall iudgement? and the firſt particular of his mercifull viſitation (wherein is his delight) is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable as man is a body. <hi>God</hi> then did viſite him in the houſe of duſt, as his laſt worke will be ioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and refining the ſame duſt againe in glory, and what might be ſaid of his viſitation in the wombe —thou ſaweſt my ſubſtance being yet imperfect, &amp;c. What of all thoſe wheeles and wyers within the body, that mill and clocke of his contriuing, of his winding vp, at thought of which <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes with a kinde of ſtrange ſhuddering. O <hi>Lord</hi> I am fearefully and wonderfully made. What of mans ſhape, ſpeech, beauty; and how largely ſpread might this webb be, if we tooke in all thoſe threds and quils of his prouidence by which hee conueyes a thouſand influences of his bounty, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen loading <hi>Man</hi> with his benefits, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. — and renewing them euery morning. <hi>Lamen.</hi> 3. light af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter darkeneſſe, ſpring after winter (as now we ſee that Gyant in his courſe ſtealing an aſcent ouer vs and ſubduing the cold;) giuing raine and fruite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeaſons, &amp;c. What addition to this, aboue all this from the nature and fabrique and faculties of our ſoule, in ſubſtance nobler then the Starres, able not onely to giue being to the body, like other
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7890:6"/>formes, but capable of eternall felicitie?</p>
            <p>Secondly, as <hi>Man</hi> is a Chriſtian, by meanes of the reuelation of Ieſus that <hi>oriens ex alto,</hi> — the day-ſpring from on wigh hath Viſited — <hi>Luc.</hi> 1. that Sunne which riſeth with healing in his wings, and this was and is a bleſſed Viſitation, for thus it runnes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> — Viſited and redeemed his people, himſelfe did Viſite and his Seruants did it in his name, riſing earely for early viſitation, and ſince his aſcenſion he ſends by his Apoſtles, Paſtors, and Teachers, that heauenly treaſure in their earthen veſſels, this manna, this light, the glory of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Iſrael, and becauſe that had not concern'd vs, it is alſo a light reueal'd to the Gentiles, this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiues vs when he is ſaid to viſit the Gentiles alſo to take of them a people to his Name. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.14. But not that word of grace, though the Word of life and power, and mighty in operation not all thoſe gratious promiſes, thoſe letters of loue indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the holy Ghoſt in proſe and verſe, which crie vnto vs to turne and looke vpon and accept the ſaluation profer'd, that ſaluation which our bleſſed Sauiour wrought for vs by ſtrong cries, and-by the effuſion of that blood which yet cries and interceed's freſhly for vs, not all theſe auaileable till the third viſitation of his Spirit, which is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called the Comforter. Comming as <hi>Iobs</hi> friends in viſitation, both to mourne and comfort him. Nay what viſitant, what phyſitian, what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour, what wife of thy boſome, what friend who is as thine owne ſoule, would ſo attend, for hee abides for euer. So Miniſter (for hee helpes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7890:6"/>
               <hi>vnâ ſubleuat,</hi> the greeke better expreſſes it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, aſſiſts in lifting againſt our infirmities) ſo pray and groane for vs, with ſighes, and groanes that cannot be expreſt, againſt all our faintings and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaires, our ſicke fits of feare and diſtruſt, giuing vs euidence, earneſt, broad ſeale of Heauen, vntill the day of our full redemption. And this is that comfortable viſitation of the ſacred ſpirit reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuely to the meanes of grace, when hee will not truſt me with the Bible alone, the ſtory of his birth and death, nor the Sermon alone, the expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and application of that ſtory, but comes after both and ſees how they worke, nay makes them worke in mee, and inables mee in ſome good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to worke by them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mans</hi> office in regard of this mercifull viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to debate and anſwere. Debate firſt, thinke what we were before he viſited. Loſt. Captiues. Enemies. Dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes. — Hee then to drop his bloud and grace, his manifold grace, preuenting, exciting, guiding, confirming; ſoftly pierceing euen into ſtony hearts, which is deſcribd by many a ſweete and amorous metaphor. theſe are his flaggons and apples, and our ſtate a marriage, aboue that too, ther's <hi>vna caro,</hi> one fleſh. But this vnion ſo high and holy, no words reach it, <hi>pereundem ſpiritum,</hi> by one and the ſame ſpirit.</p>
            <p>But what ſhall wee doe? firſt beleeue, elſe wee make <hi>God</hi> a lyar, and ther's the quarrell, when wee trample vpon, deſpiſe and count the bloud of this couenant as an vnholy thing: and if we tremble to contemne him, ſhall we dare to thinke it nothing,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7890:7"/>ſhall we take a ſolemne pride in deſpiſing his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, <hi>&amp;. eô nomine</hi> euen therefore hold a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable becauſe a Miniſter. Remember it is obſeru'd as the height a precipice of all iniquity, as farre as people could doe, or <hi>God</hi> could ſuffer, when <hi>God</hi> ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing early by them was mockt in them, the text ſayes then there was no remedy, 2. <hi>Chron. vlt. cap.</hi> But againe debate what ſhall we doe; and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle meets this conſultation. Make your calling and election ſure, and this to be done in <hi>Gods</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode: inquire after one calling firſt, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne at the wrong end. Hearken to that crie of the ſpirit within thy ſoule, the kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is within you, and not too fondly ſpend the time in ſearching thoſe roules of <hi>Gods</hi> predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and take heede of ſinking thy ſoule toward a deſpaire in his mercie, or to a ſelfe condemnation; for the Spirit of <hi>God</hi> ſpeaking peace, dareſt thou ſtill proclaime a warre, or if <hi>God</hi> haue no bill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, ſhall thy timerous conſcience bee fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vaine and carnall anſweres. Doth not <hi>God</hi> aske by way of indignation, where is the bill of thy mothers diuorce, or to which of my creditours haue I ſould thee? <hi>Eſa.</hi> 50.1.</p>
            <p>If ſo, then what ſhall I anſwere? anſwere <hi>God</hi> in obedience, all the creatures preach this anſwer; there is in all a correſpondencie. The corne, and wine, and oyle, heare vs; and the Earth heares them; and the Heauens heare it: but all heare him euen the moſt vnruly creatures are our rule, the ſtormy winde and tempeſt obeying his voice. So we, his voice without, in his Word, and his voice
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7890:7"/>too within by his ſpirit ſpeaking to our hearts, not then drowne thoſe motions, or bury them in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and wine, and worldly cares or pleaſures, leaſt ſo we quench, grieue, or doe deſpight to the ſpirit of grace, and obey him actually not in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſorie religion onely, but walke in light, and bring forth fruites worthy amendment of life.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>quid retribuam?</hi> what anſwere but a gratefull admiration, as hee that ſpake after a full apprehenſion. O Lord what is man that thou doſt ſo viſit him? This ſacrifice as hee counts it an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſo 'tis all we can offer, all we can offer him on earth, and when all things here haue end, endleſſe thanks ſhall haue their begining in Heauen. As that church in triumph there, all thoſe Angels, and all thoſe Virgins, Prophets, Apoſtles, Martyrs, with their lowd clarious and Trumpets and Harpes of gold and iuory ſtrike nothing, ſing nothing, but <hi>Halleluiah.</hi> So we that are parts of the Church mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant, ſhould exact our voices and ioyne in full Chorus. We praiſe thee GOD, we acknowledge — &amp;c. Heauen and Earth ſhall thus be full of his glory.</p>
            <p n="2">2. GODS ſecond Viſitation is in iudgement: and for ſin generall. When we finde him co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming forth of his treaſury, his ſtorehouſe of plagues, warre, famine, wild-beaſts, peſtilence, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular of croſſes, ſickeneſſe, loſſe: But 'tis the great viſitation here chiefely meant, in the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For <hi>Iob</hi> was vnder temporall calamitie now already, at the pronouncing of this text; yet (as we are <hi>viatores</hi>) in our way to take notice of this,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7890:8"/>eſpecially as it reaches his ſeruants, his choiſeſt, though with limitation, with that diſtinction euer <hi>ad correctionem, non ad ruinam</hi> and yet they fall hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, in the morning ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi> in the night ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> nay viſiteth him euery morning and trieth him euery moment, <hi>Iob</hi> 7.18. For is there not a ſwarme, an hydra and wheele of troubles in our whole life, <hi>per caput &amp; circa ſaliunt latus,</hi> (ſaith he) when roſe the Sunne ſo faire, but ere his fall ſome cloudes haue ſeiz'd on them, if not on him, ſome griefe, ſome, nay many, many perturbations, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough I'le warrant thee, for I haue <hi>Gods</hi> owne te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, Enough for the day is the euill thereof.</p>
            <p>Vpon this viſitation when it drops, when it fals, when it powers on vs. What ſhall we doe? why, firſt debate; ſtand and conſider as <hi>Iob,</hi> if all ſhould goe: Naked came I out of my mothers wombe, and naked muſt I returne. Is it the height, the depth of any grieuous affliction? What is it more then that of my Sauiour? O but he was more then man, is it more then theirs in <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. rackt, ſawen aſunder, &amp;c. Haſt thou yet reſiſted to bloud, or is it come to the fiery triall? And then in affliction, at leaſt after it, aske thy ſoule, is it not good for thee<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 11.2.</note> as the Apoſtle ſpeakes of ſtrangers, may not a man this way too receiue angels vnawares? as<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 28.16.</note> 
               <hi>Iacob</hi> on his iourney at Bethel, when hee wak'd and ſaid ſurely <hi>God</hi> is in this place, ſo <hi>God</hi> is in this viſitation, and I was not aware. I tooke at firſt no notice of his fatherly corrections, which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede his compaſſions, and conſolations: thy rod and thy ſtaffe comfort me. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 23. But now I feele
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7890:8"/>his comming to viſite mee is like his viſiting the earth, which he viſites and enriches. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65. like a Phiſitians viſiting an hoſpitall, to cure, for if I am ſure it is the hand of my <hi>God;</hi> I am ſure alſo that it is in Loue, for <hi>God</hi> is Loue, 'tis his eſſence immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. No reaſon then his viſitation ſhould prooue to an irreligious ſadneſſe, or a melancholy, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, a iealouſie, a diffidence. So long as the worke is his, though hee purge or cut, ſo hee giue me not ouer, ſo he caſt me not out of his hands; ſo I heare not that voyce which is more dreadfull then ten thouſand thunders, Depart from me, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus farre I am to debate, what am I to anſwere in affliction? Surely the beſt anſwere is no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere at all. <hi>Tacui Domine,</hi> and my ſoule kept ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, not as vnaffected, remorceleſſe, but as ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued by faith, repentance, obedience, working me to a bleſſed patience; captiuating and bringing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſubiection, euery exorbitant, euery wilde and wandring imagination. Once haue I ſpoken (ſaith holy <hi>Iob</hi>) but I will no more: or if my heart will vent, I haue formes and moldes ready wherein to caſt my words; that of <hi>Elie,</hi> It is the Lord, &amp;c. and <hi>Dauid,</hi> Behold here am I. Let him doe vnto me as it ſeemes good in his owne eyes: and I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe too, to his glory, the fruite, and the roote. I finde that thou O Lord of very faithfulneſſe, haſt cauſed me to be troubled, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. and thy viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath preſeru'd my Spirit, <hi>Iob</hi> 10.12. And to draw this into practiſe in each particular affliction, for euery one is <hi>Gods</hi> embaſſadour, and none to be diſmiſſ'd, vnanſwered. The application is a world
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7890:9"/>of matter, which I cannot looke at now: onely for that I finde my ſelfe in a Seminary, in a Colledge of Diuines, I may haue the liberty, the recreation too, to make for you and my ſelfe one particular application. For wee (my brethren) that are or ſhould bee <hi>pars indocili melior grege,</hi> if your pulſe beate like mine, are certainely ſo much infected with no worldly calamitie, as when <hi>ſaeuit malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, &amp; ignobile vulgus,</hi> as when we finde our ſelues diſgrac'd, counted the ſcumme of thoſe that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede the fcumme of the world. When all we can ſay or doe, which way ſoeuer wee frame our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or conuerſation, it is as water ſpilt vpon the ground. For though we pipe vnto them, they will not dance; though wee mourne, they will not weepe. Let a mans behauiour be like <hi>Iohn</hi> the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt; rough, auſtere, they crie he hath a Deuill: or if enlarged in freedome of conuerſation, like our Sauiour, away with him, a glutton and a winebib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, a friend of publicans and ſinners. So that the ground of the quarrell reſts not in being thus, or thus affected or qualified, or endowed, but they hate vs for our very calling. But what anſwere haue we? I could tell you one, a harſh one, of the Cynicall Phyloſopher, who being demaunded how it happened that the great and wealthy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple affected rather to bee liberall in rewarding fooles, and players, and ieſters, and beggers, then men of his profeſſion, anſwered for that they might perchance haue ſome hope of proouing ſuch them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but no hope of turning ſchollers. This was bitter: But we haue learn'd a better of the Apoſtle,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7890:9"/>I paſſe not to be iudged by you, and a better yet of a better maſter. Let not your hearts be troubled: they called our maſter Belzebub, and ſhall I not drinke of the cup which my father giues me (ſaith he) ſo ſhall wee not drinke the potion which our Lord hath begun to vs, which by taſting firſt, hee hath ſweetned for vs. Is the Diſciple greater, ſo is hee daintier then his Maſter. Were wee like the Apoſtles perſecuted, whipt, impriſon'd; that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration would make vs march on in all theſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties; and like hardy ſouldiers, <hi>non gementes ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui imperatorem.</hi> But rather reioycing that we were counted worthy to ſuffer any thing for his Name ſake: and if it came to death, wee know our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. <hi>Chriſt</hi> is to mee life, and death is to mee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage. But I forget my ſelfe, for I am bound to a further port, to that which is appointed after death; for after that to iudgement: When <hi>God</hi> ſhall viſite, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of this finall iudgement, the text informes vs two things. It ſhall be, and it ſhall be moſt dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: therefore needes debating, and caſting for our anſwere, firſt it ſhall be, hee will viſite; Euen the heathen had an apprehenſion, an expectance of ſuch a day, a time <hi>quo mare, quo tellus, correptáque re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia coeli, ardeat &amp; mundi moles operoſa laboret.</hi> All this frame vnling'd, vnpin'd, and burnt: and the new-diſcouered world haue diſcouered his too, though who diſcouered it to them, is hard to determine. But I ſpeake to Chriſtians, who as fully as wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue <hi>God</hi> in Heauen, beleeue from thence he ſhall come to iudge the quicke and the dead.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:7890:10"/>
But where, when, what, where? I know not: about Mount Oliuet; and they thinke they argue it fairely, and probably, from what we finde in the prophet of the valley of Iehoſophat, <hi>Ioel</hi> 3.2. and that of the Angels. This <hi>Ieſus</hi> which is taken vp from you into Heauen, ſhall ſo come againe, as you haue ſeene him goe into Heauen, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.11. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer that, ſure we are of this, his elect, by his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels from the foure windes, from one end of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the other ſhall bee gathered into one place, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>When, tell vs when ſhall theſe things be? you know who ask'd that queſtion, and you know our Sauiours anſwere. Take heede that no man deceiue you: and when wicked mockers ask'd it, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſets no day, he durſt not, he could not. <hi>Iob</hi> was reſolued in the article, hee ſhall ſtand the laſt vpon earth, <hi>Iob</hi> 19. but no time limited. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie father'd on <hi>Elias,</hi> tells vs of 2000. yeeres, <hi>inane.</hi> 2000. <hi>Lex.</hi> 2000. <hi>dies Meſsiae</hi> and then the conflagration. But our Sauiour controuls all, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-rules all, of that day and houre knowes no man, nor angell, nor the Sonne himſelfe. Onely by maine ſignes accompliſhed, by the Apoſtles cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thoſe the laſt dayes then, what may wee ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine now? if but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> then: <hi>a tantillum</hi> then. That ſpan of time is now contracted to an inch, and he that ſhall come, will come and will not tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. But what, what will hee come for? hee will come to Viſite ſuch a ſeſſion, viſitation, as none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it. No Star chamber, no high Commiſſion, no Parliament barre, no councell table, no inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7890:10"/>ſo formidable. Why, who comes the circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it? The LORD, the LORD chiefe Iuſtice, Iudge of all the World: wiſe, incorrupt, with power and great glory; with ſuch a traine, all his Saints, all his Holy Angels, and this is that day, the day, the great day of his wrath, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1. Of his wrath, who is a conſuming fire, and will come ſo, in fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire to render vengeance, with ſtrange effects; the Sunne obſcur'd, the Moone loſt, Starres fallen, Powers of Heauen ſhaken, the Heauens themſelues paſſing away with a noyſe, Elements melting with feruent heate, Earth, and all her workes burnt vp; 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. with the great ſound of a Trumpet, which euen the dead ſhall heare; Graues ſhall fling open their marble doores, and Seas vomite vp millions of drowned carcaſes: Hell it ſelfe ſhaking there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, and yet all this paſſing in a moment, in a twinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, falling on the world as a ſnare, ſtealing as a thiefe, rowling as the flood, confounding like light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from the Eaſt! Then for ſtrictneſſe in this Iudges proceeding as for reward firſt, wherein mens lawes are lame and defectiue, ther's a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome his owne, thy Maſters ioy, the ſame Throne <hi>Reu.</hi> 3. and then the puritie of that bliſſe, which Angels enioying adore; and laſt, the eternitie, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. at thy right hand are pleaſures for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. So contrary, thoſe foure conditions of hell torments, for variety the moſt greatneſſe inſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; for purity vnmixt with leaſt allay of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, or hope of mitigation; and for continuance euerlaſting. Is it not high time to debate and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere? and thither we are come.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:7890:11"/>
Conſider this, you that forget <hi>God;</hi> that is, you that would forget him, that would dampe out your owne light, you that ſay in your hearts, that is, you that wiſh in your hearts, there were none; what will you do? what, anſwer him? He hath anſwered me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, that you ſhall not be able to anſwer him; not able to ſtand, when he ſtands vp in iudgement, for the mouth of all wickedneſſe ſhall be ſtopp'd; your anſwer may be a vaine cry to the hils and rockes to fall and couer you from the preſence of that Iudge. But I preach not (I hope) to Atheiſts &amp; deſperates; But when Saint <hi>Peter</hi> faith, the Righteous ſhall ſcarſe be ſaued, doth hee not enforce a neceſſity of debating? Had we a triall in law, or debts on Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, wee would fall to reckoning. This is more; the title of our ſoules, and eternall Saluation is at triall: a debt doubted, and redoubled in ſinnes of youth, of age, of ignorance, of preſumption; and are our purſes nearer then our ſoules? But is there no auoyding? None, not for the yong men that are leaſt touched with remorſe: — he will bring thee to iudgement, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11. wee muſt all appeare. There are wayes, and thoſe wayes are troden too, many goe thoſe wayes, to elude the temporall iudgement of men. But in <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.12. it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: and it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: euery one muſt account, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one for himſelfe, no atturneyes, no proxies. Thinke too, thinke of our diſtance, ſhall I ſpeake to the Lord that am but duſt and aſhes? what words ſhall I chuſe, ſaith he: <hi>Iob</hi> 9.15. Alas all thought of anſwere then will bee in vaine, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that we are not able to anſwere him one thing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7890:11"/>of a thouſand: that day is his day, his day of wrath, the time of mercy is ouer, paſt, irreuocably paſt; his day of doome is come, 'tis come to ſentence, and therefore what ſhall we doe? why? while we haue time, put in our anſwere: yet the Chancery and Court of Requeſts is open. Now is the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time, now is the day of Saluation. My text is future yet, he ſhall come, he ſhall viſite. Here is a latitude for repentance; yet hee expects, calls for our anſwere, and we know to what: we haue his Bill, his Articles, Interrogatories, that is his Law written, and engrauen in our hearts: we muſt now frame and put in our anſwere: what is it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repentance</hi> firſt, for ſo may that of the Apoſtle be vnderſtood in <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. where he enioines the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſouldier to haue his feete ſhod with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of the Goſpell of peace: I know ſome take that preparation of the Goſpell for a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to preach the Goſpell, which ſhould they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long alone to vs Miniſters, others for a prompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in profeſſion, others euangelicall obedience, and ſome take it to bee patience, and not vnlikely. But may it not alſo endure this meaning of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance too? conſidering it is made the firſt ſtep in the way of life, and ſo the firſt entrance into the field, againſt Satan, by <hi>Iohn</hi> firſt, the day ſtarre, who roſe before the Sunne, and came to prepare they way: how? Repent, &amp;c. And our Sauiour in the ſame minde vpon the ſame text: Repent for the kingdome of Heauen is at hand. Sad ſighes, and prayers, and teares, make vp the firſt part of Repentance, and make vp ſo the ſacrifice of a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7890:12"/>and contrite heart, which <hi>God</hi> will not deſpiſe.</p>
            <p>And haſt thou thus? Is the rocke clouen; come drops of warme blood in anguiſh from thy heart: break there flouds of bitter weping from thine eies: This is a faire piece of an anſwere. Such teares haue a voice, that reaches Heauen, and not from <hi>Dauid</hi> onely. The Lord hath heard the voice of my wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, but from Manaſſes too: a fearefull Sinner. Becauſe thou haſt wept before mee, I haue heard it. 'Tis muſicke to the Almighties ſelfe, and raiſes a ioy in Heauen. Can the Prodigall that had wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted all his ſtocke of grace ſay but, Father I haue ſinned. See, before he can come to ſay ſo; <hi>God,</hi> he meetes him on the way, and receiues him to mercy.</p>
            <p>But this anſwere hath a ſecond part, Take heede leaſt your hearts bee hardned by ſinnes deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. It is a <hi>Circe,</hi> and a <hi>Syren;</hi> wee muſt ſtop our eares, and reſolue to bee deafe to all her charmes, charme ſhee neuer ſo wiſely, neuer ſo worldly wiſely; giuing not a faint and cold, but a peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory and ſmall anſwere with the Pſalmiſt: Away from me, for I will keepe the Commandements of my <hi>God.</hi> Will keepe them? I, that is, I haue ſworne and am ſtedfaſtly purpoſed: This is the meaning of the Apoſtle, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. The grace of <hi>God</hi> hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, teaching Vs; what? Our anſwere, — and how that? by denying vngodlineſſe, and worldly luſts. The beſt anſwere is a flat denyall, a round refuſall: like our head <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> who being tempted had his anſwere readie. And this is our firſt anſwere, in a full Repentance, made vp of griefe and Reſolution.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:7890:12"/>
2. A ſecond anſwere is <hi>Obedience:</hi> our workes for words, will not carry it. Not eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that ſaith <hi>Lord, Lord;</hi> And ſome anſweres (we reade of) ſhall not ſerue the turne. Some will anſwere; <hi>Lord</hi> thou haſt preach'd in our ſtreetes, and we haue preach'd in thy Name. Tell not mee of preaching (ſaith our Sauiour) vnleſſe your lifes haue preacht too. Away from me you workers of iniquitie. <hi>God</hi> will haue this anſwere complexio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of piety and honeſty, when theſe are married, they are crown'd with the grace and bleſſing of <hi>God.</hi> A number deceiue themſelues, as the Iewes when they cry Corbun once; as the Papiſts cracke of <hi>Eccleſia catholica Romana;</hi> ſo theſe conclude all lies in beeing profeſſours: zealous magnifying themſelues, and deſpiſing others. But what were the Phariſees? by Chriſts owne teſtimony, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and yet wicked. People may draw neere with their lips, and their hearts farre enough off. If thou haſt faith (faith Saint <hi>Iames</hi>) let vs ſee it: Let your light ſhine: how? why in action ſhine, or elſe to bare profeſſion, our Sauiour threats a round and proportionall anſwere. At that day I will profeſſe to you, I know you not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiection.</hi> But will the weake ſoule ſay; May I truſt to theſe anſweres: May I firſt truſt to my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance? I feele indeede the weight of ſinne, and finding the offence of an infinite Iuſtice, I am hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly afraid, deiected, like <hi>Dauid,</hi> when hee ask'd his ſad ſoule: why art thou ſo heauy? I am ſo: ſo wounded, pierced, ſtrucke thorow, and my heart rebounds into my eyes. I weepe, and I crie migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7890:13"/>for mercy: but can I helpe it? Is not ſinne a Serpent, a Sea, a Fire, a Poyſon? was I not ſtung by this Serpent, drown'd in this Sea, miſerably ſchorcht by this fire, enuenomed in the whole maſſe of my nature with this corruption before I was borne? And ſince alas I haue added to this Ocean: put fewell to this fire, helpt to infixe this ſting, and worke into my heart the contagion: and then am I able to reſolue againſt ſinne, to deny vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe, to reiect the tempter, to giue my Iuſts their finall anſwere. I finde indeede naturall men, morall men, when they will compound an happy man, put in this as one ingredient, <hi>reſponſare cupidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, &amp; ſibi imperioſus,</hi> enabling him to checke and controule, to Commaund and ſubdue rebellious paſſions, by the dictates of rectified reaſon: And their ſeuerall anſweres, to diuerſe corrupt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are enough to ſhame me, and all that profeſſe themſelues chriſtians. But were they able to keepe their owne rules, or am I able? What to hate ſinne ſo as I ought, with a perfect hatred. I flie ſome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normous vices for feare of Lawes. But <hi>tolle peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clûm, iam vaga proſiliet, &amp;c.</hi> and though I know there is death in the pot; the wages of ſinne is no better; though I pull the fruite and taſte it, and prooue it to be naught but gall and bitterneſſe, nay barrenneſſe and ſhame: Yet ſuch is my madneſſe, to purſue a new ſhame, and ſeeke death in the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of life; falling like a birde or a beaſt: Nay no bird, no beaſt, would ſo oft fall into the ſame ſnare, ſame pit, into the ſame ſinne whereof I haue againe, and againe, repented me.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:7890:13"/>
What then ſhall I doe? Shall I rely on my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond anſwere: and truſt in my owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Some bold men dare doe ſo; and dare teach others ſo; dare boaſt a ſtocke and treaſury of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and ſatisfaction. But Lord I find the language of Canaan, thy holy Word, and the cries of thy holy ſervants farre otherwiſe. I finde thy <hi>Bernard</hi> ſay: <hi>Nolo: Horreo meritum.</hi> Thy <hi>Dauid,</hi> O Lord, if thou enter into iudgement, no fleſh ſhall be iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And thy bleſſed Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> I finde another law haling me, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. and therefore I heare him crying ripe, to ſay, O miſerable man, who ſhall deliuer me? Theſe are yet the eiaculations of an humble ſoule, asking, ſeeking, knocking at the gate of heauen, and this very debating, is a fruit of the Spirit, growing on to a perfect anſwere. In Men's conſultings &amp; reſoluings for worldly affaires, they may, they doe vſually miſ-count, miſ-carry; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune choaks their artillerie: But in theſe holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions, the end is euer gratious, ſucceſſe glorious. If the Iailor in the Acts, and Saint Peters hearers come but to a wounded conſcience, to be prickt at their hearts, and to cry, What ſhall wee doe? Marke what followes, and how faſt it followe: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, repent, be baptized and ſaued. Saued, how? by beleeuing in him that is able to frame a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent anſwere. Hee that made them wonder at his gracious anſweres, and to whom no man was able to anſwere a word. Who was that, and where is he to be had? If any man ſinne, any man that finds himſelfe a ſinner, Let him put his anſwere to his aduocate: for we haue him, ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> wee
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7890:14"/>haue an aduocate <hi>Ieſus Christ the righteous.</hi> He is the propitiation for our ſinnes. Take then thy Shield of faith, and quench all the fiery darts of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. This is the new and liuing way of anſwering God by his Sonne, by the blood of <hi>Ieſus, Hebr.</hi> 10. May not then the Chriſtian beleeuer haue acceſſe with boldneſſe: for ſhall both bleed for ſinne, or ſhall hee bleed in vaine? <hi>Peccaui peccatum grande,</hi> ſaith he, I haue committed an hainous ſinne: yet on my faith and repentance, I will goe to God, &amp; ſay, Lord thou canſt haue but blood, merit, ſacrifice, ſatisfaction, exact obedience. Take then thy Son <hi>Ieſus:</hi> He is all theſe, and all theſe to me: for he is mine, I receiue him by faith, and I finde comfort, hope, liuely hope, full aſſurance in him. I will not therefore flie with <hi>Cain,</hi> and cry with him, My ſin is greater, no thy mercy reioyces againſt ſinne, and now therefore there is no condemnation to them that be in <hi>Christ Ieſus.</hi> My anſwere then to thy bill is, it was torne, when his bodie was torne, 'Tis can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled, and was nail'd to his Croſſe: My debt was great, but is pai'd to the vtmoſt farthing. Thy wrath let it be a cup, he hath drunke it of; Let it be more, a whole Wine-preſſe, he hath trode it alone. I will then put on my Lord <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and come in the rayment of my elder brother, and be roab'd in his innocencie, and canſt thou then denie me? No thou canſt not, thou mayſt as well denie thy ſelfe: for if I haue it faire to ſhew vnder thy owne hand: Euery gratious promiſe in thy Goſpell is ſuch, yea this was thine owne act in my ſaluation: For God was in Chriſt reconciling the world to himſelfe.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7890:14"/>But may I not prodigally and preſumptuouſly fling away my ſoule in a vaine confidence of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie? Yes, many doe ſo, that will do nothing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, not when they haue the aſſiſtance and prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of helpe from heauen. Therefore I will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound and put all theſe anſweres together. I will truſt to my Sauiours merit: but I will repent too, and pray too, and worke too, and ſo worke out mine owne ſaluation, with feare and trembling. And though I haue no holineſſe of mine owne; and without it no ſeeing thee at the day of iudgement, yet thou the God of my peace wilt ſacrifice me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that day. 1. <hi>Theſſal</hi> 5. O bleſſed and full an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere now! and O bleſſed condition of ſuch hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie ſoules, ſo farre from affrightment at thought of the Iudges comming that they ſhall then reioyce, and lift vp their faces, and in the meane time are of the number and Communion of thoſe Saints that loue his appearing, looking for, and haſting to the comming of their Lord in glory, calling &amp; crying: Bow the heauens and come downe; and, Lord how long? and come Lord Ieſus, Come quickly.</p>
            <p>I haue done with the explication of my Text. There is a fourefold application. Firſt, in generall, to the land and ſtate, whereof we are a part: God hath perform'd his office of a Viſitour ouer vs; both wayes: In mercie. Thus long preſeruing vs, and extending peace ouer vs as a floud, euen then, when it hath beene a Sea, a red Sea of bloud and ruine round about vs. Viſiting vs in his vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancy, and defeating our enemies blaſted attempts, in 88. In the Powder-Treaſon. Giuing vs ſtrange
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7890:15"/>and miraculous deliuerances amongſt them not the leaſt; the bringing backe our preſent Royall Soueraigne from the hand and land of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. How many other wayes hath this holy watcher from his circle and ſeate of heauen viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs, and kept vs vnder his wings of gratious Prouidence; and if he had not, would not our foes by this haue rooted out our name from vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and the name of Engliſh Proteſtants beene no more in remembrance; for wanted there either might or malice in them; hoping and proiecting oft to haue made our land like Sodome, clouds of Pitch, and heapes of aſhes. But the ſnare hath bin hitherto ſtill broken, and we yet deliuered by his gratious and mercifull Viſitation. That ſecond way of viſiting in iudgement the Lord hath alſo of late begunne to trie amongſt vs, by that plague, which ſwept away ſo many thouſands, and by the lowd and dreadfull ſound of warre in neighbour Countries, that haue really taſted, and actually en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured, all that propheticall deſcription: The noyſe of weapons, rowling of garments in blood, ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their houſes, rauiſhing their wiues and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, and breaking their children in peeces, before their eyes: And theſe things befalne ſuch as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue from vs a tender and deare reſpect, we being wounded through their ſides; or if theſe acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents beyond the water, will not waken vs, God hath his way in the Sea (faith the Scripture) and we might haue markt his dealing with vs there, for a long time being able to doe no good there, and our enemies able to doe vs much miſchiefe from
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7890:15"/>thence; God hath his way in the earth and vnder it, and we haue felt him there, ſenſibly perceiued his mighty hand from thence; in the ayre, he hath his path too, and walkes vpon the wings of the winde, and there he cauſd thoſe rotten vapours to blend themſelues into a peſtilent defluxion, and powre their virulence on the earth. And if wee take into conſideration the preſent brauerie of the enemie abroad, and our home-diuiſions, our great boughs beating one againſt another, no man that is not extreamely ſtupid, but will eaſily finde that God is angry with his people, and that our ſinnes deſerue the haſtning of the laſt iudgement, in the other element of violent fire. And then what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men ought we to be (ſaith the Apoſtle) in holy conuerſation? How watch, pray, and ſtriue to anſwere him reſpectiuely to theſe viſitations. But alas, for his mercifull viſitation haue we been reſponſible ſo much as in thankefulneſſe? O no, it is our nationall ſinne. Secure ingratitude wherein we ſleepe and dreame away our liues without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of that gracious God, — <hi>qui nobis haec otia fecit.</hi> Who hath ſo preſerued vs. And to his ſummons and warning-pieces of his angry vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation haue we return'd our repentance, or our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and doing good: I lookt for that, ſaith God by his Prophets, thats his aime in ſtriking, I lookt for righteouſneſſe, but behold a crie: a lowd and fearefull cry compos'd of all our crying ſinnes together, and the cry continued and enforcd to ſuch an height, that we cannot heare his voice cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to vs, nor he in heauen heare the cry of his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7890:16"/>peoples Prayers, it is ſo drown'd and ſwallowed vp in this <hi>Tumultus peccatorum.</hi> What then ſhall we doe? Euery man ſearch into his owne ſoule and drag thence his moſt beloued ſinne, and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice it as an offring acceptable to God, before that laſt and dreadfull viſitation here ſpoken of in the text, ſpecially ſuch oppreſſors as are threatned with his comming, in <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.5. And ſuch dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drunkards as the Age produces now, who were warn'd by our Sauiour with a ſpeciall Caueat. <hi>Take heed lest your hearts be ouercome with ſurfeiting and drunkenneſſe, and ſo that day come vpon you vnawares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I am to touch vpon a paire of ſinnes heere coupled in this Chapter, and to which my Text hath ſpeciall relation, and this I call the ſecond ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, and my returne to ſpeake of the cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence which I promiſed. The firſt is Adulterie: for of that is mention made before, from the 9. to the 13. verſe, implying, the hainous and dangerous nature of this ſinne, as one of thoſe which we ſhall finde moſt vnanſwerable at the day of iudgement. Euery heathen authour hath ſome impreſſions of this. <hi>Tacitus</hi> in his Poeme reckons amongſt fiers and ſlaughters, great adulteries as a plague and cauſe of plagues. <hi>Horace</hi> —<hi>hoc fonte deriuata clades, &amp;c.</hi> What might bee added of the defilement, diſgrace, infection and danger to the agents, their poſteritie, the whole land? <hi>In popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, patriamque fluxit:</hi> with ſuch a flow as brought the flood on the old world, to rince and ſoake it cleane from this pollution, and brought <hi>Gehennam è Coelo,</hi> Hell out of Heauen vpon the Sodomites, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7890:16"/>therefore cauſed <hi>Dauid</hi> to call and crie for all the ſtreames, the whole Ocean, according to the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of thy mercies; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5. One place of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may ſtand for all the reſt, that 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.3. Whereas if <hi>God</hi> had required nothing elſe; or at leaſt Sanctification did mainely conſiſt in this. So hee ſpeakes enforcingly, This is the Will of <hi>God,</hi> euen your Sanctification, that you ſhould abſtaine from fornication, that euery one of you ſhould know to poſſeſſe his veſſell in Sanctification, and honour; not in luſt of concupiſcence, as the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles that know not <hi>God.</hi> We finde by this, what is the Will of <hi>God:</hi> and what then ſhall <hi>Men</hi> doe, what ſhall they anſwere him? Firſt euery <hi>Man</hi> cite himſelfe <hi>in foro,</hi> in the conſiſtory of his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, then conuicted; (for who is free in all, when our Sauiour extends this ſinne euen to a luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eye?) to flie and auoide it, and for our owne ſtrength is weakeneſſe, to pray for aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt to ouer-ſhadow vs, and learne from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Holy <hi>Men</hi> to anſwere this tentation. <hi>Ioſephs</hi> anſwere, Shall I doe this wickedneſſe and ſinne againſt <hi>God?</hi> Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> anſwere, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. Shall I take the members of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and make them the members of an harlot, <hi>God</hi> forbid.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſinne to which the words of my text haue immediate reference is Rigor and cruelty to Inferiors: why is this ſuch a matter? May I not vſe my ſeruant at my pleaſure, no: it ſeemes ſo by <hi>Iohs</hi> queſtion here, and yet in his time ſeruants were ſlaues, but euen a little, but euen one degree aboue beaſts, the Maſters being owners, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7890:17"/>power of life and death, and no doubt but theſe ſlaues (as amongſt the Turkes at this day) felt and endured inhumane and cruell vſage in the world. Wee read of a number of inſolent exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples among the Romans, and <hi>God</hi> himſelfe confin'd his owne people, and pinn'd them downe with Lawes, and ſtill controules the riſing of their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie by remembrance of their owne condition in Egypt: and for that very end the holy Ghoſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds here with a double argument againſt ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolencie: which <hi>Tremelius</hi> calls <hi>elegantiſsimam</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the firſt argument drawne, ſaith he, <hi>à Iudicio Dei,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the iudgement of our common <hi>Lord</hi> and Maſter, reſpectleſſe of any mans perſon, and therefore the deſpiſing, either of his perſon, or of his cauſe, yea of ſuch a cauſe as wherein hee dares contend with mee, that am his Maſter; euen this, <hi>God</hi> will not beare. I muſt anſwer for this; nay I ſhall not be able to anſwere it, if I be guilty but of this. And the ſecond argument is taken <hi>à iure naturali,</hi> in the 15. verſe, Is my mold or mettle better then my mans? Is a Lords fleſh and bloud, of a purer compoſition then his groomes, or his footemans? Did not hee that made mee in the wombe, make him? and did not one faſhion vs in the wombe? or faſhion vs in one wombe, that is the common wombe of our mother Earth: What is then the leſſon hence, but meekeneſſe for all to practiſe, but ſpecially thoſe in vpper place, ſince none is more ſuperior then a Maſter ouer his ſlaue; and for this purpoſe the Scripture preſents vs with two ſtrange examples. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſo choſen to aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7890:17"/>by <hi>God</hi> himſelfe. So knowne of <hi>God</hi> as his friend. Dignified by his miraculous power in the eyes of his enemies, and by the conduct of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that neuer man more prompted to take ſtate vpon him, and yet it is ſaid this <hi>Moſes</hi> was the weekeſt man alive. The other is <hi>Dauid</hi> when hee danc'd before the Arke, and <hi>Michol</hi> reproouing him, hee told her he would be more vile: Since ſo ſhe called his humilitie, and confeſſes the bottome of his heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 131. I haue behaued my ſelfe and quieted my ſoule euen as a wearied child. Wee finde this was (at leaſt they ſaid ſo) in the intent of thoſe Philoſophers both Sceptique and Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rean, to arriue at <hi>Manſuetudo, &amp; Tranquillus ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> to cleare the ſoule like a faire, and vnclouded Heauen, and this was brought vs by the Doctor of Heauen <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> both in precept. Learne of me to bee humble and meeke, and in patience poſſeſſe your ſoules; and in practiſe, ſtooping himſelfe not to a ſaruay of our miſeries: but clad, encloſed, compaſſed with all mans infirmities, ſinne onely excepted: and as vnaſham'd, as glorying in his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, he cries out; tell the daughter of Sion, not her Seruant, but her Soueraigne, her King, the King of Kings, comes vnto her meeke. — And is it not then a miſerable conſideration: a wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſpectacle, to ſee a proud man and an humble <hi>God,</hi> an angry, impatient, and a mercileſſe man, and yet a <hi>God</hi> of Loue, and long-ſuffering. I looke to Heauen, and thence I finde deſcending the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of the World, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is his deſcription in <hi>Heor.</hi> 1.3.) the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7890:18"/>brightneſſe of his Fathers Glory, and the expreſſe image of his perſon, in ſhape not onely of a man but of a Seruant; Hee that commands legions of Angels, and whoſe attendants they were in the wilderneſſe, and proud of the office, to ſerue him as his cookes &amp; butlers: And ſhall not this example worke on mee, that am but duſt and wormes? and keepe mee from inſulting ouer inferiours, who though my ſeruants, and my meaneſt Hines and drudges are yet reſpecting him our Lord and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther both my fellow-ſeruants, and my fellow-bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren?</p>
            <p>Obſerue the prouocations to this vertue. Hee ſcornes the ſcorner, reſiſts the proud, but giues grace to the humble. The Meeke he will guide in iudgement, in his iudgement, hee will teach them his way, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25. when he ſhares the world he tels vs, the Meeke ſhall inherit the Earth, and delight themſelues in aboundance of peace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.7. which he ratifieth in his bleſſing, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.5. But this is earthly bleſſing, is it not heauenly in things ſo? Heare him in his Prophet<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 61.1.</note> 
               <hi>The Spirit of the Lord God is vpon mee, becauſe the Lord hath anointed mee to preach good tydings,</hi> (and we know what that meanes) to whom, to the <hi>Meeke.</hi> His firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming was for the <hi>Meeke,</hi> in the ſame Prophet, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 11.4. and (to meete againe with the text) when <hi>God</hi> ſhall viſite, when this Sonne of <hi>God</hi> ſhall ſtand vp to ludge, and to caſt all proud, and barbarous, and cruell diſpoſitions into Hell. So he will then lift vp the <hi>Meeke,</hi> and neuer leaue theſe poliſht iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els till he hath inſet them in Heauenly Glory. For
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7890:18"/>the Lord takes pleaſure in his people, and will beautifie the <hi>Meeke</hi> with ſaluation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.4. And therefore who is a wiſe man, ſaith Saint <hi>Iames, Ia.</hi> 3.13. let him ſhew out of a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation his workes in meekeneſſe of wiſedome: for ſuch is Heauenly Wiſedome, at <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, eaſie to bee intreated, full of mercie, &amp;c. If we preach, it muſt be in Loue, and the ſpirit of <hi>Meekeneſſe,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>vlt.</hi> If you heare, receiue with <hi>Meekeneſſe the Word, Iam.</hi> 1.21. If wee will both Preacher and Hearers walke worthy our vocation, it muſt bee with all lowlineſſe, and <hi>Meekeneſſe, &amp;c. Ephe.</hi> 4.2. For as if in this one grace all the reſt were lock'd and infoulded, ſo doth the Apoſtles ſpeake there, and reckoning vp the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall gifts of the ſpirit in <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. They ſeeme all to be but <hi>Meekeneſſe,</hi> diuerſified to ſeuerall names. To end, I beſeech you (brethren) by the <hi>Meekeneſſe</hi> and gentleneſſe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> be yee clothed with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie; and vpon that reaſon which is here in my text, <hi>God</hi> viſits for rigour; he reſiſts the proud, but giues grace to the humble, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.5.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, if crueltie exclude from Paradiſe, and diſable from ſtanding in the day of viſitation. Vſe this for terrour againſt all the terrible Ones vpon earth, all exalted and cruell oppreſſours: They muſt heare of the wrath of this ſuperuiſor in Heauen, who ſees them from thence, and from thence they ſhall in that day ſee him come to viſite for this ſinne. Though they can ouerſoare and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape all power on Earth, yet ſee what a day the Lord threatens to make in <hi>Amos</hi> 8. and ioyne to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7890:19"/>that the propheſie of <hi>Eſa.</hi> 10.1.2.3. &amp;c. <hi>&amp; Ierem.</hi> 6.6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, extend this for Conſolation. <hi>Regum ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendorum in proprios greges,</hi> ſaith hee, the higheſt power on Earth, can ſtretch but to their Vaſſalls: but ouer Princes themſelues in his prerogatiue and dominion that here ſtands vp in my Text, and of whom <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, hee is higher then they. In the cauſe and quarrell of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> then we muſt, then put on the reſolution of thoſe three valiant Children. The <hi>God</hi> whom we ſerue is able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. but if not, we will not diſobey his command, for any countermand on Earth. And in this all thoſe poore Saints of <hi>God</hi> that groane vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Turkiſh yoke or Spaniſh inquiſition, all thoſe poope tennants and ſeruants that liue rackt and oppreſt and ground to powder, vnder the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſſe and rigorous Lords and Maſters muſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance the eye of their ſoules, with comfort to the comming of this great and glorious Iudge and Lord of Heauen: for that day of his viſitation ſhall be alſo the day of their full redemption. My third application is to foure ſorts of viſitours. Firſt, you that are authorized ouer vs, you ſee <hi>God</hi> will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge his office: doe you ſet <hi>God</hi> euer before you, his example, and his feare, and firſt learne his firſt viſitation in mercy, in kindeneſſe to vs your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to doe vs good. 'Tis <hi>God</hi> (we confeſſe) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points degrees of Superiority and excellence in all. Orders of Angels in Heauen, in the Skie grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, leſſer lights. Lower ſtill, Eagles and Flies, Cedars and Shrubs, among the very Stones, the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7890:19"/>brighteſt tincture giuen to the Ruby, cleareſt light to the Diamond. But by comparing parts of the body, the Apoſtle prooues the head cannot want the foote, among vs ſpecially of the clergy, no proud inſulting, for the rule holds on this ſide the water too, that the Capuchin, and Cordelier, the poorer part of this Tribe, vphold the dignity of Prieſthood, ballancing with the pompe of ſome ſuperiour prelates.</p>
            <p>Secondly, doe you viſite as <hi>God — ad correctio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> and not hold it a vertue, <hi>laxare diſciplinam.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the worlds intertaining Mahumetiſme is aſcribed to three cauſes. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tis Arrianae, Manichaes furores;</hi> and the third <hi>d ſciplina laxata.</hi> But wherein doe we neede your inſpection? in both our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and our life. Firſt, ſee to our inſufficiency, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance; what ſilly things ſuffered not onely to reade, but (clothing their fancies with pretext of the Spirit) to preach too; and then the maine way of teaching in many places yet vnpractiſ'd and that is Catechiſing. Alas! what is it to enrich the peoples cares for an howre, who if they ſleepe not, gape, and praiſe the Sermon, as they like the tune ſaith <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> as they doe a Loue-ſong, <hi>Eze.</hi> 33.32. Then are you ouer mens liues too, ouer the Layety to curbe, their woluiſh and fox like ſhifts and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenage in the Lords portion; but chiefly in that ſinne whereto my text appoints you in <hi>Gods</hi> ſtead: for whore mongers and adulterers, <hi>God</hi> will Iudge, he will viſite, does it dayly, and will then doe it dreadfully. In the meane time are you his Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Delegates, Commiſſioners. What though
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7890:20"/>the ſcornefull fooles as <hi>Salomon</hi> cals them, make a mocke of this ſinne, a ſport, and purſue it as an art and trade: Yet you know it is (reſpecting a mans ſelfe) vnhallowing of <hi>Gods</hi> Temple, a diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the body of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> reſpecting others, and defiling of the moſt holy and ſolemne couenant on Earth, a keruing aſunder thoſe whom <hi>God</hi> hath ioyn'd, and therefore ſtands the Commandement forbidding it, betwixt Theft and Murder. Laſtly, reſpecting the Land, it is a fire as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeakes here, at <hi>Ver.</hi> 12. deuouring foundations and hurling the flame round about it. And are not they who haue power of coercion, if they doe it not, as ſo many ſpreaders of this fire, as ſo many bawds, and pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars, if for bribes they wilfully palliate, or winke at this diſorder, or looke vpon it through a falſe and colour'd <hi>medium.</hi> And if euer there was cauſe to cry loud and lift vp the Trumpets voyce to wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken both you and the whole ſtate, is it not now, when like Egypt plagu'd with Frogges, the Land euen ſtinkes of this corruption, and had we no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther infection, enough to bring ſome fearefull curſe vpon vs all.</p>
            <p>But are our liues ſo cleare, they neede no viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, neede none from you? no? Is not a debaucht and drunken miniſter within your powre? Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, a crime hatefull in the lay, but hideous in the cleargie man: a ſin in them, but ſacriledge in vs; And are not you to viſite for theſe things, and vindicate our mother from this ſtaine? But when? when ſhall we ſee a great and rich adulterer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the open penance of the Church? Or when
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7890:20"/>ſhall I heare an Arch-deacon, a Commiſſarie, a Chancellour, or a Biſhop rather, (for thats the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of God here an Ouer-ſeer,) rattle and fright ſome of theſe ſwolne and putrid offall of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites: theſe hatefull roaring drunkards, in the midſt of the aſſemblie of their brethern. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member God in his viſitation on Sodome, ſaith he will goe downe, and ſee whether ſo or no: So ſhould you, ſtay to inquire, and not make the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation (as the Countrey calls it in ſcorne) a buſie taking onely, or paſſing ouer vs like a viſion rather then a Viſitation.</p>
            <p>But who ſhould helpe it? how can there any thing be reformed without preſentment? this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes a ſecond ſort of Viſitors: Church-wardens: And what ſaith your bill my Maſters: Some poore Raſcall will not pay his leuie, or the p per hath got a baſtard: but how many hath your Land-lord got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten? Alas, Sir, we are poore people, and it would be our vndoing to m ddle with ſuch. But what your Miniſter? they ſay, is a lewd Toſſe-pot, a very drunken Sot. O no! <hi>Omnia benè,</hi> a good Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; a little giuen to company keeping: thus the beſt of you are content to mince it, or ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps readie to defend him, and reaſon why: they keepe the Ale-houſe, and he's the prime gueſt: if it were not for him they might knocke downe the ſigne. Bleſſed be God I am perſwaded you know not manie ſuch as I deſcribe, but yet I fear'd there be ſome ſtill within the compaſſe of theſe markes. And dare not you preſent them? Nay, dare you preſent any thing? Shall men in office, Viſitours,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7890:21"/>Wardens, nay Watchmen ſworne thus play with their oaths? What a wretched thing is it thus to feare men and deſpiſe God? That great Lord Warden of his Church, who when he ſhall viſite you, for this periurie, what will you anſwere him?</p>
            <p>A third ſort of Viſitours are our ſelues, Seers call'd in the old Teſtament, and Ouer-ſeers in the new. <hi>Acts</hi> 20. all Biſhops. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. Let vs then learne to diſcharge it, firſt by heeding and viſiting our owne hearts; reflecting on and examining our owne ſoules, whither the God in our Bookes, in our Sermons be ſuch in our ſecret breſts, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we heare or feele our ſelues rather when wee preach, or whether our preaching run not through vs like a wooden Spowt, like the old riddle of Through the wood &amp; neuer touch it; neuer touch, neuer affect the heart. And then ore looke our learning, and ſtriue to mend our nets, giuing our ſelues (as <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith) <hi>recoquendos,</hi> till wee become workemen that need not be aſham'd, diuiding the word aright, able to exhort and conuince ſoundly, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.3. for this is <hi>Ars artium, regimen animarum,</hi> which to performe as commonly 'tis done, flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly, or lazily and perfunctorily, is both eaſie and acceptable, but it is too moſt miſerable and damnable. And then ore-ſee our liues and thoſe exempt and defend from baſeneſſe, but ſpecially that odious ſinne, which goes too much in blacke, drunkenneſſe. The way to make the Seer ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene, to loſe the eyes of his minde, to drowne his holy vnction in drinke, and ſuffocate the Spirit of grace, he muſt be apt to teach (ſaith the Apoſtle)
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:7890:21"/>and addes, not giuen to wine, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine be not drunke with wine, but fil'd with the ſpirit, as if the firſt would emptie vs of the ſecond. Briefly, ſee to your charge, whereof the holy Ghoſt hath made you ouerſeers. 'Tis an high truſt. God makes me ouerſeer of his will, that will wherein he hath bequeathed ſo many gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Legacies, and ſhall I not diſcharge this truſt: and reueale the whole Will of God. What though the people complaine not, the Court takes no very ſtrickt bond of vs; will not God require it? Sonne of man, I will require their blood at thy hand, and the Apoſtle therefore pronounc'd himſelfe free from the blood of all men, becauſe he had diſcloſd the whole counſell of God. Thinke of the Apoſtles and Paſtors gone before vs; Speake and teſtifie you glorious companie of Apoſtles in heauen, and you goodly fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of antient Prophets, is there a roome in your royall armie for that cowardly or lazie ſouldier, that betraies or preuaricates the cauſe of his Lord and Sauiour, and reſpects not the precious ſoules of his people? Thinke on the Deuill, what a carefull Viſitor, how he goes about like a Lion roaring after his prey, compaſſing the earth, and his agents and factors thoſe mountebanke Ieſuits, that creepe into houſes, and leade captiue our ſilly women; boaſting of their conqueſts and victories and triumphs, and are in danger of being dull'd by aſſiſting at ſo frequent conuerſions. Which though I take for a braue lie of the ſhaueling, yet let vs learne ſedulitie from theſe our profeſſed aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7890:22"/>Laſt of all, if nothing elſe, let the reward ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance our induſtrie. When the great Biſhop of our ſoules, who now cries, <hi>Paſces oues,</hi> and vrges vs, be inſtant in ſeaſon, &amp;c. will in due ſeaſon viſit vs, and if he come and finde vs ſo doing, as he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, we know the bleſſing by heare ſay now, but ſhall feele and taſte it then; and becauſe we cannot comprehend it, we ſhall then be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended of it: We are not able to conceiue it now, it cannot enter into vs, but we ſhall enter into it then: <hi>Well done good and faithfull ſeruant: Enter into thy Masters ioy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude all, We all are Viſitors, as men, and as Chriſtians to looke to our bodies, eſtates, elſe worſe then infidels, to viſit God in his holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to meet him often and grow familiar with him, in his Word, Sacraments, in our Prayers, to doe theſe things while the doores of his Temple are open, and the Goſpell offer'd, leſt there come a famine, or a darkeneſſe ſeize vpon vs, and then to viſit men the Saints and Seruants of God, and not thoſe that are rich onely, for they haue many friends, many viſitants too, too many euen to a wearineſſe, <hi>tota ſalatatrix turba peregerit orbem,</hi> like walking ghoſts, tormenting whom they viſit, but God would haue his poore members regarded, Papiſts will tell you of pilgrimages and trauailing to ſhrines, but not the dead images, but theſe liuing images are in Gods Care, and if we care for his fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall doome at that laſt and moſt dreadfull day of his great viſitation, wee muſt viſit them, when poore and naked, and ſicke and in priſon, or elſe be
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7890:22"/>viſited then for our not viſiting now. <hi>Goe ye curſed into euerlaſting fire.</hi> But if we doe our dutie in this hoſpitall below, wee ſhall bee chear'd and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh'd with him and them in his dining Roome, in his palace of heauen aboue, with a <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt application of the Text is in our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to God: <hi>O Lord, our great and gracious Viſitor, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7890:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7890:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
